<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--This tutorial is from gamermaker.io: https://gamemaker.io/en/tutorials/make-arcade-space-shooter-->

<?xml-model href="salemme_09_23_Relax_NG_03.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <title>Make Your Own Arcade Space Shooter</title>

    <sect num="0">
        <body>
            <nl>We’ll build this game in three simple steps:</nl>
            <list>
                <step num="1">Program the ship to move</step>
                <step num="2">Make space rocks explode</step>
                <step num="3">Finish your game</step>
            </list>
            <nl>Download GameMaker <link>https://gamemaker.io/en/account</link> and let’s
                begin!</nl>
            <link>https://youtu.be/nwlvT-L9vFg</link>
            <nl>[ 1 Move Your Ship / 2 Destroy Rocks / 3 Finish Your Game ] </nl>
        </body>

    </sect>


    <sect num="1">
        <head>How to Create a New Project</head>
        <body>
            <nl>Open GameMaker. You'll see a “New” button – click on it.</nl>
            <nl> Here you can start with a blank project, or choose a template.</nl>
            <nl>For this game, let's use the "Space Rocks" template. This gives you all the images
                for this tutorial.</nl>
            <nl>Enter a "Project Name", and hit "Let's Go!".</nl>
            <nl>You're now in your project!</nl>
            <nl>The Asset Browser on the right contains all your assets. You'll now see four
                Sprites, which are images you can use in your game. </nl>
            <nl>There’s “spr_player”, the ship you’ll fly, “spr_bullet”, which you’ll fire from your
                ship, and two rocks, which you’ll destroy.</nl>
        </body>
    </sect>

    <sect num="2">
        <head>How to Use The Asset Browser</head>
        <body>
            <nl>In the same Asset Browser, we want to create some objects. An object is how you
                bring an image to life, by programming it to move, shoot, or do anything you need it
                to.</nl>
            <nl>Your ship, rocks, and even the bullets you fire are created as objects. We’ll put
                these in the “Objects” group in the Asset Browser, which is currently empty.</nl>
            <nl>Right-click on the “Objects” group, and select “Create -> Object”. Change its name
                from “Object1” to “obj_player”.</nl>
            <nl>Press F2 to rename your selected object, or right-click on it and select
                “Rename”.</nl>
        </body>
    </sect>

    <sect num="3">
        <head>How to Edit an Object</head>
        <body>
            <nl>Your new object has an editor. Here you change its properties, and program it, which
                we’ll do very soon.</nl>
            <nl>Every object needs a sprite – otherwise how would you see it? </nl>
            <nl>Click where it says “No Sprite”, and from under the “Sprites” group, select
                spr_player.</nl>
            <nl>We need some more objects now. Just like you created obj_player, create three more
                objects:</nl>
            <list>
                <step num="1">obj_bullet: This is the bullet your ship fires. Set the sprite to
                    spr_bullet.</step>
                <step num="2">obj_rock: This is the rock you’ll destroy. Set the sprite to
                    spr_rock_big, as every rock will start big, and shrink as you shoot it.</step>
                <step num="3">obj_game: This is a “silent” object that will manage your game. It
                    doesn’t need a sprite.</step>
            </list>
            <nl>These are all the objects you need! Let’s now place these inside a level.</nl>
        </body>
    </sect>

    <sect num="4">
        <head>How to Make a Level in GameMaker</head>
        <body>
            <nl>Each “level” in GameMaker is a room asset. Look in the Asset Browser – there’s one
                already there for you: </nl>
            <nl>Double-click on it. The “Room Editor” will open, where you’ll build your level.</nl>
            <nl>Before doing anything, I want to resize the room to make it a 1000x1000 square.</nl>
        </body>
    </sect>

    <sect num="5">
        <head>How to Resize a Room in GameMaker</head>
        <body>
            <nl>Look at the lower-left corner of the window - you'll see an "Inspector" window.</nl>
            <nl> Here, set the Width and Height of the room to 1000. You can use a different
                size.</nl>
            <nl>If you don't see these options, go into your Asset Browser and click on Room1. They
                should be visible while the room is selected.</nl>
        </body>
    </sect>
    
    <sect num="6">
        <head>How to Place Objects in a Room</head>
        <body>
            <nl>Look at the left panel in the Room Editor: there are two layers created by default,
                “Instances” and “Background”. </nl>
            <list>
                <step num="1">Instances: This is an instance layer. Your objects go here, just like
                    cereal goes into a bowl.</step>
                <step num="2"> Background: This is a background layer. Change the background colour
                    or apply an image.</step>
            </list>
            <nl>Click on the “Instances” layer to select it – this is where your objects will
                go:</nl>
            <nl> From the Asset Browser, drag obj_player and place it in the room. </nl>
            <nl>Your player ship is in the room now, as an “instance” – you can place multiple
                “instances” of any object in the room!</nl>
            <nl>Do this with the rocks – drag obj_rock into the room multiple times, until you have
                around six instances:</nl>
            <nl>The stage is set for the play. We just need to teach the actors their roles.</nl>
        </body>
    </sect>
</root>
